Sultan Altamimi

BI Lead Architect





913-717-9577



sultan.s.altamimi@gmail.com



New York, NY



Education

MASTER'S DEGREE Information and Technology University of Northern Iowa

BACHELOR OF SCIENCE Electrical Engineering University of Northern Iowa

Expertise

Data Integration Data Warehouse Design Reporting (KPIs, Metrics)

> **BI** Architecture **Analytical Skills** Ad Hoc Query **Data Modeling**

Automated Monitoring and Alerting Data pipeline batch and stream processing

Certification

Infosphere DataStage 11.3

Microsoft:

Microsoft Certified: Azure Data Engineer Microsoft:

MCSA Business Intelligence Development





Profile

Technical background, combined with strong leadership and management skills, with over 18 years of experience in data modeling, data warehouse design, development, implementation, and maintenance of relational databases and data warehousing using Microsoft BI, IBM as well as cloudbased data storage across multiple sectors such as Insurance, Health Care, Telecom, Financial, and Utilities on large-scale and highly visible projects

Experience

EisnerAmper, New York City Metropolitan Area

Oct 2021 - Present

Business Intelligence Lead Architect

Build an enterprise data warehouse that consolidates data from various sources, such as operations and finance. Build and provide analytical and dashboard tools. Providing user-friendly datasets and data models for business users for self-servicing reports to reduce the need for report customizations and reduce report maintenance by the BI team.

- Lead the BI and EDW development team and drives the transformation and BI efforts by modernizing analytics and applying best practices
- Managing Data Life Cycle, ETL Design, Data Governance, and Change Management.
- Analyze, evaluate, and develop long-term strategic and operational plans for the enterprise to ensure that the EA objectives are in alignment with the enterprise's longterm business goals.
- Experience in leveraging and designing integration patterns to take advantage of Azure Modern Data Architecture patterns including use of Azure Data Lake Gen 2, Azure Synapse Analytics, Data Pipelines, CI/CD processes, Az DevOps, web services
- Analyze and translate business requirements into conceptual and fully detailed logical data models and create logical data models based on existing applications and databases.
- Oversees projects and initiatives to develop data solutions from multiple sources and identify processes for automation

Forrest T. Jones & Company, Kansas City MO

May 2017 - Oct 2021

Business Intelligence Lead Architect

Migrate old legacy systems (DB2, AS400 and Oracle) to SQL server 2016 and Azure cloud base system. Gather data from web base systems into a centralized data warehouse where business users can analyze data to improve their overall operation and cost.

- Work as a team lead architect for one of the Legacy System replacement Projects at Forrest T. Jones. Responsibilities include gather requirements, design, and develop SSIS ETL Processes, delegate work to team members, mentor junior team members and ensure deliverables are met on a timely manner by coordinating the team activities.
- Design and Develop data warehouse solutions using Microsoft BI stack (SQL server and Visual Studio, Power BI, Azure Data Factory, and cloud computing)
- Expert in Extraction, Transforming and Loading (ETL) data flows using SSIS, DataStage Designer; creating mappings/workflows to extract data from Oracle, SQL Server, DB2 and Flat File sources and load into various Business Entities

Westar Energy, Topeka KS

Jan 2014 - May 2017

Lead BI Engineer

The project involved the development of an application, which provides a web-based user interface that serves as a single point of entry into the integrated systems environment. The developed software also provides access to generate custom reports and queries from the Operational Data Store (ODS) and Enterprise Data Warehouse (EDW).

- Bult ETLs using DataStage to extract data from xml, JSON, csv, txt file and Web Services through Classic Federation server, Column Export, Column Import, Sequential file, Transformer, Aggregate, Row Generator stages in accomplishing the ETL Coding.
- Perform integration with external data sources including Oracle databases, SQL Server databases, Metadata, Flat files (fixed-length and delimited), XML files, Web Services (SOAP).
- Worked with IBM team to install DataStage/WebSphere, Linux RedHat servers and setup all 3 environments (Dev, Qual and Prod) in cluster nodes and configure the connections between Engine Tier, Services Tier and Repository databases.

Sultan Altamimi

Business Intelligence Architect

Integration Tools

SQL Server Integration Services (SSIS)
SQL Server Analysis Services (SSAS)
Azure Data Factory
IBM DataStage
Informatica
Apache Spark

Development Tools

SQL Server Management Studio
Microsoft Visual Studio
Azure DevOps
Microsoft SQL Server
Power BI
Azure Pipelines
IBM Infosphere
SQL Server Analysis Services

Database/Data Storage

SQL Server

Azure SQL Database
Azure Cosmos DB
Oracle
IBM DB2
Netezza
PostgreSQL
Azure Blob
Databrick
Data Lake

Data Modeling Tools

Synapse Analytics

Embarcadero ER/Studio dB Forge Studio IBM Infosphere Data Architect Erwin Idera ER Studio

Programing Languages

Transact-SQL (T-SQL)
PL SQL (Oracle)
Power Shell
C#, C++
Unix Shell Scripting
Java

DAX wer Que

Power Query M#

XML

Jason

Python

Scala

Experience (Continued)

Sprint Corporation, Overland Park KS Data Warehouse and ETL Developer

May 2011 - Jan 2014

Performance management tool that contains operational and performance metrics for Cellphone towers. Flux collects then aggregates and calculates data from each cellphone towers/sites 24/7 before processing data into downstream reporting purposes which allows Sprint's network team (RF Engineers) to monitor the health of Sprint's cellphone towers

- Involved in the Sprint's Network Vision initiative covering 3G CDMA&EVDO modernization and 4G LTE from the OEM (Original Equipment Manufacturer) data standpoint as well as CM(Corporation Management) for reporting purposes
- Interact with multiple groups: Sprint and Ericsson Services National RF engineers, Requirement Teams from vendors (Lucent, Moto, Ericsson, and Samsung) and Windows Team System Admins.
- Monitoring and analyzing KPIs to identify areas of investigation to reduce Lost Calls, Ineffective Attempts,
 Failed connection attempts. Dropped Connections.
- Conduct network performance Data Analysis to troubleshoot and fix network problems relating to network capacity and switches.
- · Review, create and correct mapping documents as well as revise the code (TSQL) for the SSIS packages.
- Work closely with Clients/Business Analysts to define data requirements for reporting warehouse.
- Provide the ETL production status of the system in the daily Flux Health meeting.
- Strong Applications Development experience with back-end databases such as SQL Server, Oracle and MS Access using ADO/ADO.NET, OLEDB, ODBC and SQL client.
- Created Indexes to get the high-level performance.
- Performing the ETL operations to support the incremental, historical data loads and transformations using SSIS and DataStage
- Develop advanced shell scripts, SQL scripts in support of database operations

Object Technology Solution, Overland Park KS

Aug 2008 - May 2011

BI Developer/SQL Server

Hospital measure analysis project for North America's leading children's hospitals. They are widely known for their excellence in caring for America's children. CHCA is to fulfill the medical needs of children and have access to medical products and services designed and manufactured to meet the unique needs of children.

- Developed hospital measure analysis dashboard using Universe and WEBI.
- Design and developed universe for measure analysis dashboard and reports.
- Developed Pie charts, bar graphs, line graphs, comparative graphs and trend graph in WEBI reports.
- Worked closely with account managers and business managers in calculating requirements for implementation on Business Objects 4.0.
- Worked on Business Objects Security as per the Client requirement.
- Developed Performance Management Dashboards to set goals, measures and monitor KPI for Balance Scorecard initiatives.
- Created new Universes on Business Objects 4.0 relating to HR.
- Worked on Web Intelligence 4.0, Crystal Reports Enterprise 4.0 and Dashboard Designer 4.0.
- Experienced in BOE Migrations from BO XI and BO XI R2 to XIR3.
- Developed documents like BOBJ Security, Xcelsius, Web & Universe Designer etc.

IDOT/UNI, Cedar Falls IA

May 2005 - Aug 2008

SQL Server Developer

Wireless Damage is a research project to monitor and detect bridge damage in the state of Iowa. It was funded by Iowa department of transportation to track the health of Iowa highway bridges.

- Involved in creating the log files to track the bugs raised as a part of development and while in the production.
- Identified damage on the general operational condition of bridges and monitored bridges structures using wireless sensor nodes
- Analyzed the existing application and wrote technical specification document for the reports associating with the application.
- Worked on WCF Service layer to retrieve data from the SQL Server.
- Analyzed the requirements and created model classes accordingly to be used in the application.
- Used Visual Studio BI tool to create SQL server reporting services (SSRS) reports.
- Responsible for Database Script updates and Query writing related all the modules